All right.
So our Web site is still looking a little bit sparse and in fact it's looking nothing like this is it
but we're going to change up very very quickly.
Let's go ahead and add the rest of the content in order to have all the images that we need for our
top section.
Now in this lesson if you look at the resources you'll find a zip file that you can download and once
you extract that zip file you shall have a folder called CSSA my site images.
Now you double click on this folder you'll see two images.
One is a cloud.
Another is a mountain.
And we're going to try and recreate the scene that they've got over here.
So let's go ahead and add those images to our project folder.
So if you pull up atom and find your project folder then we're going to go and create a new folder in
here called images and inside this images folder is where we're going to drag and drop those two P.N.
the cloud and the mountain.
So we're going to put it inside here so that we can use it inside our Web site.
So now we're going to go ahead and look at our images so that we have a image of a cloud at the top
of our top container.
So the source will be images slash cloud dot PNB and the alt text will just be cloud image and we're
going to have another cloud below this paragraph.
And finally we're going to have an image of our mountain right at the bottom.
So that will be images flash mounted up here in G and the alt text will just be mounted image.
All right.
Let's hit save and let's refresh to see what our page looks like right now.
Now it looks a little bit weird right.
Why is it that this cloud is taking up its own line and it's not next to either this heading or this
paragraph tag.
But this cloud is on the same line and next to this mountain image what is going on here.
Well to understand this we have to look at the CSSA display property.
Now the display property has four different values and we're going to look at them in turn and see what
each one of these does.
Now if we switch on pesticide again you can see that the box around the cloud is only as large as the
image as is the box around the mountain.
And this cloud.
But the box around the H H1 and also the paragraph element there as long as the width of the page.
So what's going on here.
Well by default some elements are what's called block display.
For example this H1 and this paragraph tag and block elements are those that take up essentially the
whole width of the screen on a web page.
So effectively blocking out any other elements from sitting next to it on the left or on the right.
Now the most common block elements that we would have seen already are our paragraph's our headers so
H-1 through to age 6 divs or lists and list items as well as forms.
And if we have to code pen and I'm just going to create a new anonymous pen let me just get rid of the
Geass editor and I'm going to have my view with my editors on the right.
So now I'm going to go ahead and create two block elements so we know that paragraphs are block elements.
So let's create a paragraph called Hello.
Another one called world.
Now if I select the paragraph tag in my C Ss and I give them both a background color of say red then
you can see that the entire paragraph takes up the whole width of the web page.
So it's blocking any other element from being on the same line next to it on the right on the left.
Now here's a related problem.
Say if I wanted to look at this paragraph TYG which we now know to be a block element.
What if I wanted to style the pro part of it differently from the rest of the words in this paragraph
tag.
How can I only target one part of this paragraph tag.
How can I say for example underline the word pro so that says a programmer but style these three characters
differently.
Well some of you might think that I could just split up this sentence into three paragraph tags.
So what if it was a plus a space then it was pro and then it was grammar a programmer.
So now I've got this separate paragraph tag for the word pro and I can give it a class of say just the
word pro and I can go into styles and style it differently from the others so I can say Doc pro and
this one if you do a little bit of research on google you'll find that in order to make it underlined
you just have to change the text decoration to underline Now what happens in this case let's check it
out.
You can see that because the paragraph element are blocking elements.
They take up the entire width and they block everything else from being on the same line as themselves.
This doesn't actually work even though we've been able to target just one part of that line.
We can't have it looking like this.
So let me show you the solution instead of having three paragraph tags.
So let's just undo this to where we were before and we've got a single paragraph element.
What we can do is we can use another ational element code a span and inside the span we can add that
word pro and we can give that span a class of Pro.
And because we've already selected that class in C Ss and we're making that part underlined then that
is going to be applied to the word in this span.
Now if we hit save and we refresh you can see that we've achieved what we set out to do.
And this sentence is still on the same line.
Now why is that if we switch on pesticide once more.
And I hold down the control key.
You can see that over here.
I'm hovering over the entire paragraph element but one part of it has a span and this allows us to select
almost like as if you would highlight a section of your text just select one part of the text in order
to formatted or style it differently.
Now the reason why I'm showing you this here instead of inside the Shamal module is because spans like
divs don't do very much unless they used in conjunction with CSSA.
But another reason why I'm showing it to you now is because the span element is what's known as an in
line display element.
So unlike block display elements for example the heading and also the paragraph element in line display
element only takes up as much space as it needs to in the height and in its width so you can see that
the box around the span is only as large as it needs to be as is the box around our cloud and also our
mountain.
So some of the common inline elements that you're going to come across are things like span's image
elements and also your anchor tags.
If you think back to our C-v Web site that we created in our H.M. module Billing's for our hobby's Web
site and our contact me web site they show up next to each other.
And this is because they are in line elements and they do not block other elements from occurring on
the same line.
In fact they encouraged them to.
And so this is why they called in line elements.
Now if we head back into our code pen and we create another spanne
now while you can have spans the nested inside paragraph tags or H ones or whatever else it may be.
You can also have them as dandelions but you can see him if we select our span element and we also give
it a background color
then you can see that these elements are in line.
And even if we had a whole bunch more of these spans they would continue to be stacked onto the same
line until we run out of space horizontally.
Now you might wonder why would we ever use block elements if we can simply use inline elements.
Surely it seems far more flexible.
Well there's just one problem with inline elements.
You can't actually change the width.
So if I said the width of all the spans should be 100 pixels you can see that absolutely nothing happens.
But if I specify a with the same with two block elements then you can see that it complies very eagerly
but it still doesn't let any other element sit on the same line.
So what can you do.
Well you can actually change the display property of any given element so I can make a paragraph element
which we know is by default a block element.
I can change its display value to be in line and that makes all of our paragraphs inline elements and
allows everything to sit next to each other on the same line.
But you can see we've just lost the ability to change its width now.
Similarly I can change the display property of our inline elements to block elements and this allows
me to change its width but it doesn't let them sit on the same line.
So what should I do if I wanted elements that can occupy the same line but at the same time I can set
their wits.
Which one should I choose then.
Well you don't actually have to choose because there is another type of display which is called the
in line block and this kind of gives you the best of both worlds.
So if instead of changing the paragraph element to inline I'm going to change it to inline dash block
then you'll see that not only am I allowed to change its width you can see that it's now a hundred pixels
wide but I'm also able to make them go onto the same line.
So act almost like in line elements.
And this is kind of what image elements are like.
By default.
Now I say kind of because as always reality is much more complex than that.
But if you're interested I'll provide a link to more discussion around this.
But for our purposes we're just going to treat images as if they are in line block elements because
we're able to change its width and height to whatever it is that we desire.
And they also get displayed as if they're in line elements next to each other.
So we now covered three out of the four display values that we have access to.
The last one is simply display none.
And that just gets rid of our element.
So let's head back into our code pen and I'm going to give our second paragraph element a separate class.
I'm going to call this second P and I'm going to target it down here.
DOT.
Second p.
And I'm going to set its display value to none and you can see what that does is that it simply removes
that element from the website as if it didn't exist.
So if I get rid of this display block and allow our span's to continue being inline elements you can
see that there's no gap between the first hello and the second hello world paragraph has now completely
disappeared out of the flow of the document as if it never was written inside the code.
It's almost like I've just gone ahead and deleted it from the HMO.
But of course I haven't and all that I've done is just said its display value to none.
Now when you try to figure out how to hide things on your web page for example if you had a quiz then
you might want to hide and show the answer.
There's two ways that you can do this.
One is display none as you've seen here.
Which takes the element out of the flow and it's as if it never existed.
The other one is a property called visibility.
And this you can set to hidden and what this does is that it makes that element disappear but it keeps
its original position and all the other elements still flow around it as if it's still there.
It just can't be seen anymore.
So whenever you're trying to make things disappear or reappear.
Think about what effect you want to have and choose between these two properties.
So as we've seen in this lesson the position of elements on screen are determined by many things.
The box model the margins the size of the border the size of the width and the height of the actual
element.
Whether if its display block or whether it's display in line whether if are allowed to set it with or
if we're not.
But even before CSSA comes into play you have to remember that there's already rules that govern how
you HVM all elements should be displayed on screen.
So to learn about that and to learn more about CSSA positioning or see you on the next lesson.